Guide to the Yale University School of Medicine Miscellaneous Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Incoming Letters to the Dean or the Yale Administration, 1810-1886; Series I
  - Incoming Letters: W-Wh (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Walker, Alfred Eastman, to Lindsley, 1867 June 29
      Walker (B.A., 1864, M.D., 1867) asks if his undergraduate course in chemistry would qualify for medical school course and for his being able to take the examination for M.D.
    - Welch, F. G., to Lindsley, 1869 October 27
      Student asks if he can delay payment of fees.
    - White, Moses C., to Noah Porter, 1881 October
      On financial issues including salary of professors, payment of student fees, and money left over for apparatus. Written as a "private estimate" rather than the "official estimate." "Examined and approved by B. Silliman."
    - White, Moses C., to the Prudential Committee of Yale College, 1882 June 21
      His dissenting assessment of the reasons for the "depressed condition of the Medical Department." See folders 36 and 38.
    - White, Moses C., to Noah Porter, ca. 1881
      He personally opposes as unfair the hiring of instructors at the high salary of $1200. See folders 36 and 38.
  - Incoming Letters, Wi-Z (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Wilcox, Lucian S., to Moses C. White, 1877 August 11
      Acceptance of the chair of theory and practice of medicine.
    - Wilcox, Lucian S. to Franklin B. Dexter, 1877 September 15
    - Williams, Lewis, to Lindsley, 1868 July 14
      On his coming to New Haven to serve on the Examination Committee.
    - William Wood & Co. to Lindsley, 1866 June 21
      Proposes that the school advertise in the Medical Record.
    - Woodford, Clayton, to [Lindsley], 1866 August 5
      Concerning the misunderstanding by which he did not get a gratuitous course of lectures. (See letters from Charles Carrington, and from Connecticut Medical Society, folder 3).
    - Young, Francis J., to Lindsley, 1865 July 18
      Young (M.D., 1866) requests an annual circular and asks if he may now take the gratuitous course of lectures he was recommended for in 1862.
- Committees and Internal Records, 1819-1886; Series II
  - Committee to Nominate Professors, 1829-1886 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The Committee to Nominate Professors nominated physicians to the President of Yale and the Yale Corporation to fill vacant chairs in the medical school. For almost all of the period, the Committee was a joint committee of representatives of Yale and the Connecticut Medical Society. Afterwards, the faculty of the Medical Department nominated professors and lecturers.
    - Nomination of Thomas Hubbard and William Tully, 1829 June 24
    - Charles Hooker, Secretary of Connecticut Medical Society, to Jeremiah Day, 1833 May 8
      On the membership of the joint committee.
    - Nomination of Andrew Harris or Jonathan Knight to be Professor of Surgery, 1838 July 18
    - Nomination of Charles Hooker to be Professor of Surgery, 1838 August 13
      He was nominated after Harris and Knight declined.
    - Nomination of Charles Hooker, 1839 August 6
    - Nomination of Henry Swainson as Professor of Materia Medica, 1841 December 28
    - Nomination of Worthington Hooker, 1852 February 3
    - Recommendation that Benjamin Silliman and Eli Ives be continued as emeritus professors, 1853 June 2
    - Nomination of Leonard J. Sanforth, 1863 May 6
    - Nomination of Stephen G. Hubbard to be professor of obstetrics, 1864 March 17
    - Letter of Connecticut Medical Society (Moses C. White, Secretary), 1873 May 31
      Certifying the representatives of the Connecticut Medical Society on the Committee to Nominate Professors
    - Nomination of David Paige Smith to be professor of the theory of practice of medcicine, 1873 June 10
    - Transfer of David Paige Smith to the chair of surgery, 1877 July 30
      Report of Benjamin Silliman, M. C. White, and L. J. Sanford claiming that it is the power of the faculty with the consent of the President of Yale to transfer faculty from one chair to another.
    - Nomination of Lucian S. Wilcox, 1877 September 12
    - Nomination of James K. Thacher to the chair of physiology, 1879 June 16
    - Board of Professors nominating clinical lecturers and assistants, 1879 June 12
      Letter continued September 24, 1879.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter nominating new professors and lecturers, 1879 October 11
      Lists members of Connecticut Medical Society on the Committee to Nominate Professors and informs Dexter that the Medical Faculty requests two other professorships, a chair of ophthalmology and otology for William H. Carmalt, and a chair of clinical surgery for Francis Bacon. Also requests the nomination of two lecturers.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter for the Board of Professors nominating lecturers and assistants, 1879 October
      Board of Professors in Medical Department nominate H. P. Stearns as "Lecturer on Insanity," William Carmalt as "Lecturer on Ophthalmology," M .D. Mann as "Lecturer in Gynecology," and Herbert E. Smith as assistant to the professor of chemistry.
    - Nomination of Frank Beckwith and T. Mitchell Prudden for professorships, 1880 June 28
    - Lindsley to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1881 June 27
      On the transfer of William Carmalt to the chair of surgery
    - Lindsley to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1881 June 27
      Recommendation of T. Mitchell Prudden as lecturer in histology for one year.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1883 June 23
      On the appointment of various lecturers for the year.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1883 October 1
      Nomination of C. Purdy Lindsley to be demonstrator of anatomy.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1884 June 20
      Requests appointment of various lecturers for the year and their salaries.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1885 June 23
      Requests appointment of lecturers for the year.
    - Herbert E. Smith to Franklin B. Dexter, 1886 May 19
      Herbert E. Smith followed Lindsley as Dean. Requests appointment of Samuel W. Williston as assistant professor and appointment of various lecturers and assistants.
    - Herbert E. Smith to Franklin B. Dexter, 1886 May 21
      Addresses for Dexter to notify appointees.
    - Herbert E. Smith to Franklin B. Dexter, 1886 June 28
      Nomination by the medical faculty of James Campbell as professor of obstetrics and Henry Swain as a lecturer.
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1819-1829 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Folders 18-23 contain letters or reports from the Committee of Examination for the Medical Institution of Yale College to the President and Fellows of Yale College listing those students who passed the examination and should be awarded an M.D. For most of this period, the Committee consisted of members of the Faculty and members of the Connecticut Medical Society. The list for 1822 is missing..
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1830-1839 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Missing 1835
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1840-1849 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Missing 1848
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1850-1859, 1852-1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Missing 1850, 1851, 1858
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1860-1879, 1863-1878 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Missing 1860-1862, 1864-1869, 1873, 1879
  - Committee of Examination: Candidates for M.D., 1880-1889, 1880-1886 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Missing 1881, 1882, 1887-1889
  - Notes on qualifiations of applicants for admission, 1877, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Report of a committee on admissions (Moses White and Stephen G. Hubbard), 1877 October 18
      Notes on the qualifications of five students and whether they should be accepted and whether fees should be reduced.
    - Results of a preliminary examination of candidates for admission, 1882
      Scores on examinations in physics and mathematics and whether the candidates passed. Only 5 of 11 candidates passed both examinations.
  - Student petitions to the Dean and Medical Facutly, 1851-1878 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Class of 1852 to "Gentlemen of the Medical Faculty", 1851 December 8
      Asking for a public event the day after examinations at the end of their studies to commemorate their graduation. The class recommends a valedictorian and a class poet.
    - "Statement" of Cornelius Wade Bull to the Medical Faculty, 1863
      Bull (Yale College, 1863, M.D., 1867), a current student from Tallahassee, Florida, requests to take his second course of lectures gratuitously as a county student because of his recent loss of access to property in Florida. He has voted in New Haven.
    - "Petition from Students 1877-78 for Obstetrical Clinic", 1877-1878
    - "Petition for a course of lectures on Medical Jurisprudence", 1878 April 9
    - Petition "Respecting Public Exercises at the Close of Terms", 1878 November 21
      Because of the class's "misfortune" in electing a valedictorian, the class petitions to omit the graduation exercises this year and that the medical faculty should in the future name the valedictorian.
    - Petition of senior and junior classes to exempt them from the newly required preliminary examination, [1878]
  - Microscopical anatomy prize, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    4 items concerning a student prize funded by Dr. Edwin Bentley for the best microscopic specimens on pathology or surgery.
  - Committee on Obstetrical Instruction, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Leonard J. Sanford and C.A. Lindsley, Report of Committee on Providing Obstetrical Instruction for 1880-1881. The draft report is addressed to "Chairman."
  - Letters from the Dean and Medical Faculty to the President of Yale College, 1868-1882 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    The Rev. Theodore Woolsey served as President of Yale College from 1846 to 1871, followed by the Rev. Noah Porter who was President from 1871 to 1886.
    - Lindsley to Theodore Woolsey, 1868 July 20
      Objecting to supposed assumption by the Corporation of appointive power
    - [Lindsley] Interview with President Woolsey, 1868 July 22
      On the above issue
    - Francis Bacon and Moses C. White to Noah Porter, 1874 December 7
      On the need for funds to make improvements to the medical school's Museum.
    - Lindsley to Noah Porter, 1874 December 8
      2 items. Statement of amounts advanced by professors for current expenses.
    - Lindsley to Noah Porter, 1874 December 15
      On advances made by professors for expenses of the school.
    - Lindsley to Noah Porter, 1881 June 27
      On the desirability of printing Porter's address on David Paige Smith
    - D. A. Cleaveland and Benjamin Silliman to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1881 June 27
      They were appointed a committee to request a portrait of the late David Paige Smith.
    - Lindsley to Noah Porter, 1882 April 13
      Vote of the Medical Faculty on changes in tuition to be submitted to the Prudential Committee. The faculty recommends $125 each for the first two years and $75 for the third year.
  - Letters from the President of Yale College to the Dean or Medical Faculty, 1864-1867 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Theodore Woolsey to Jonathan Knight, 1864 March 31
      Corporation overrules Knight's and two other professors' objection to the appointment of Stephen Hubbard.
    - Theodore Woolsey to Lindsley, 1865 November 6
      Requests the Medical Facuilty's opinion on a document (not included) that he received.
    - Theodore Woolsey to Lindsley, 1866 June 30
      On Dr. Hill's proposal on teaching dental surgery. See folder 5.
    - Theodore Woolsey to Lindsley, 1866 July 15
      On Dr. Hill's proposal on teaching dental surgery
    - Theodore Woolsey to Lindsley, 1867 July 8
      He has arranged a meeting of the Committee on Nomination of Professors and would like some of the professors to speak on the need for more professorships and "the qualifications of the men you have thought of." Requests a list of medical graduates from last January.
  - Letters from the Dean or Medical Faculty to the Secretary of Yale College, 1879-1885 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Franklin Bowditch Dexter was Secretary of Yale College and of the Yale Corporation from 1869 to 1899.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter (postcard), 1879 September 15
      On teaching medical jurisprudence.
    - Lindsley to Frankin B. Dexter, 1880 April 9
      Acknowledgement of appropriation of $1000. Also a copy of this letter.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1880 April 9
      Request that the Corporation pay professors annual salaries, and that student fees be paid to the Treasurer of the College.
    - Benjamin Silliman, Jr. to Franklin B. Dexter, 1883 April 13
      As President of the Governing Board of the Medical Department, he informs Dexter that Lindsley will perform the duties of the chair of theory and practice of medicine.
    - Lindsley to Franklin B. Dexter, 1883 October 7
      On requirements for graduation.
    - Lindsley to William Carmalt, 1884 June 23
      On Carmalt submitting to the Corporation a vote concerning the Keese prize fund.
    - Herbert E. Smith to Franklin B. Dexter, 1885 October 24
      Changes in duties of certain professors.
  - Letters from the Secretary of Yale College to the Dean, 1874-1880 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    These letters are Dexter's notices of action taken by the Yale Corporation on financial and other matters.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 1874 December 17
      Appropriation of $500 from general funds for the benefit of the Medical Museum.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 1875 December 9
      Corporation endorsed the bylaws submitted last June. See folder 32.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 1876 June 29
      Appropriation of $500.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 1877 June 29
      Appropriation of $500 and possible rental of a building for the Dispensary and the building of a chemical laboratory.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 27 June 1878
      Appropriation of $500; representatives of Yale appointed to confer with the Connecticut Medical Society concerning amendments to the charter of the Medical Institution. See folder 37.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 1879 June 24
      New charter of the Medical Department was not approved by the Corporation because of a particular section of the law which gives authority to the Connecticut General Assembly to amend or repeal the charter.
    - Franklin B. Dexter to Lindsley, 26 October 1880
      Appropriation of $1122 which includes payment of $200 to Moses White for undertaking extra work in obstetrics; lecturers were approved; notice of a statute regarding students dismissed from one department who apply to another.
  - Letters from the Dean or Medical Faculty to the Treasurer of Yale College, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Henry Coit Kingsley was Treasurer of Yale College from 1862 to 1886.
    - Stephen G. Hubbard and Lindsley to Henry C. Kingsley, 1877 Feb 14
      They were appointed to be a committee of the Medical Faculty a provide a statement of the resources of the Medical Department, and they request information on interest on investments.
  - Letters from the Treasurer of Yale College to the Dean or Medical Faculty, 1877, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Henry C. Kingsley to Stephen G. Hubbard and Lindsley, 1877 February 15
      Lists investments of the Medical College but denies as improper the other information requested.
    - Henry C. Kingsley to Lindsley, 1880 March 24
      On the legacy from Mrs. Keese for the Keese Prize Fund.
  - By-Laws of the Medical Department of Yale College, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    These by-laws on the internal governance of the Medical Department were approved as amended by the Corporation on December 9, 1875.
  - Financial Statements and Reports of the Medical Faculty, 1875-1881 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Statements and reports of the Dean and Medical Faculty to the Prudential Committee or to the President and Fellows of Yale College. These show that the Medical School was operating on a very limited estimated budget (from $2200 to to $5800) and that expenses were greater than annual income. Each year the Medical Faculty, through its Dean, C. A. Lindsley, requested the Corporation to provide funds to make up the difference. At least some of these documents are drafts or copies kept by the Medical School.
    - Lindsley to the Prudential Committee of Yale College, 1875 September 18
      Financial Statement of the Medical Department. 2 items.
    - "Estimate of Expenses for Ensuing Year", 1875 September 18
      Signed by C. A. Lindsley and M. C. White for the Committee on Expenditures. 2 items.
    - Lindsley to the Corporation of Yale College, 1876 June 24
      The Medical Faculty requests an appropriation to meet current expenses for the year. The Committee on Expenditure has estimated expenses for the ensuing year.
    - "Estimate of Expenses for Ensuing Year", 1876 June 24
      Signed by C. A. Lindsley and M. C. White or Committee on Expenditures.
    - Request of the Medical Faculty for an appropriation (draft), 1876 June 26
    - Lindsley to the Corporation of Yale College., 1877 May 10
      Request for an appropriation to cover expenses.
    - "Estimated Expenses of the Medical College from, July 1, 1877 to July 1, 1878"
      Signed by M. C. White and C. A. Lindsley
    - "Reported Cost of Allegreth Refrigerating Room", 1878 March 7
      "Examined and found correct by L. J. Sanford, March 7th, 1878."
    - Faculty of the Medical Department to the President and Fellows of Yale College, "Report on the Financial Condition of the Institution for the year ending June 1st 1879", 1879 June 25
      Detailed report listing the estimates expenses for fiscal year 1879, the actual expenses, and the estimated expenses for financial year 1880. Signed by C. A. Lindsley and M. C. White, "Committee on Expenses."
    - "Financial Condition of the Medical Department of Yale College", 1879 August 1
    - "Medical Institution of Yale College, Annual Statement of Finances, with Estimates for the Year from June 1st 1878 to June 1st 1879"
      Signed Moses C. White and C. A. Lindsley
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, "Report of the Financial Condition of the Medical Department", 1880 June 26
      Signed by C. A. Lindsley, M. C. White, and W. H. Carmalt, Financial Committee.
    - "Confidential Estimate of Expenses Medical Dept: 1881-82"
    - Memorandum, 1881 June
      The Medical Department requests funds to pay for the lectures by T. Mitchell Prudden and to purchase projection apparatus, a spectroscope, and apparatus to illustrate chemical physics.
    - "Annual Budget" (Copy), 26 October 1881
      Discusses the bequest of David Paige Smith of a large collection of surgical instruments. Signed by Moses C. White, C. A. Lindsley, W. H. Carmalt, "Committee of Med. Faculty."
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, "Report for the year ending Sept. 1, 1881 with estimates for the year ending Sep 1, 1882"
      Signed Moses C. White, C. A. Lindsley, and W. H. Carmalt, "Committee of Medical Faculty."
    - "Budget of Expenses for 1884-5", 28 April 1884
  - Financial papers: Receipts, 1869-1881 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    7 items
  - Memorials to the President and Corporation concerning the New Haven Dispensary, 1877-1879 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1877 June 19
      On the need to negotiate with the New Haven Dispensary to facilitate clinical instruction in the Medical Department. Resolution of the faculty that the house adjoining the College be leased for the Dispensary. Signed by C. A. Lindsley.
    - Petition of members of the medical Faculty to the Corporation of Yale College ("not sent"), 1879 June
      Petititon to formally recognize the teaching of the attending physicians at the Dispensary by appointing them instructors in the Medical Department. Not signed. (See Benjamin Silliman (Jr.) to Lindsley, June 20, 1879, in folder 13.)
  - Dissolution of the agreement between Yale and the Connecticut Medical Society, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Resolution of the Connecticut Medical Society, S. B. St. John, Secretary, 28 May 1884
      Resolution to cancel the articles of agreement between the Yale Corporation and the Society made in 1810 and any subsequent modifications.
    - Report of the Committee appointed on behalf of the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1884
      On dissolving the formal relationship between the Medical College and the Connecticut Medical Society. Signed by Frederick J. Kingsbury and Henry B. Harrison.
  - Other Memorials of the Medical Faculty to the Yale Corporation, 1830, 1872-1882 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Jonathan Knight, Memorial of the Medical Faculty on the need for a separate course of lectures on obstetrics and diseases of children, 1830 September 7
    - Draft resolution on the admittance of women to the Medical School, [1872] October 18
      In pencil. Would accept women only if they are admitted to the other departments of the University.
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, "A Memorial" (draft?), 1873 March 25
      "A brief statement of the critical condition of the Medical Department," signed by S. G. Hubbard, Francis Bacon, and Benjamin Silliman. Contains a lengthy discussion of why there are not as many graduates as formerly.
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1873 June 24
      Resolution that the Dickerman property adjacent to the Medical College be purchased.
    - Medical Faculty to the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1873 June 24
      Memorial on the "critical condition" of the Medical Department, the desire to adopt the three-year graded system, and the need to raise an endowment. Cooperation with the Connecticut Medical Society to secure an endowment has been "unproductive of practical results." Signed by Stephen G. Hubbard and Moses C. White, Committee.
    - Committee on Expending the Museum Appropriation, Report, ca. 1874.
      Signed by C. A. Lindsley and M. C. White. Report on how the $500 appropriated should best be spent. Draft.
    - Lindsley to the Prudential Committee of Yale College, 1875 June 11
      On the "disposal of the shed water from the rear of the College Building."
    - Request for funds for an instructor in histology and assistant in chemistry for one year, 1882 June 28
      Pencil draft, unsigned. See Moses C. White to Noah Poter, n.d., folder 14.
  - State Legislation, 1866, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Connecticut General Assembly, May Session, 1866, "An Act in alteration of an Act, entitled "An Act in relation to the Medical Institution of Yale College"
      Printed Act with manuscript annotations for updating.
    - Connecticut House Bill No. 95, "An Act to Incorporate the Medical Department of Yale College", 1879
  - Miscellaneous, 1832, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Announcement of Medical Institution of Yale College, 1832
    - Invitation to Graduation Exercises, 1841
      Addressed to Mr. and Mrs. Dyer White.